Welcome back. Today we are going to get a deep knowledge about IP address. IP stand for internet protocol.
So, here we are going to understand a deep in IP types of IP and how it works actually in actual real world.
Now, whenever you connect your device, whenever you connect to a system to your Wi-Fi to the internet, you receive IP.
IP address, which is a logical address for your device. So, the logical address is the one that keeps changing.
Every time after a few days you can see it will change. Even you can remove it from your own by using the same day.
Okay, we will talk about the same-day command prompt and how we can use that in our network operations.
Heck, daily we have to use same-day when we are doing in a storage operation. So, welcome to this foundation guide on IP address.
So, today's intent connected world understanding how the device communicate is equation. You will explore what IP address are, why they are, since I learned, deal into that two types of IP address, IPv4 and IPv6.
What is an IP address? IP address is a unique numerical level designed to assign to each device can do to a component of a device entered protocol for communication. Think of it as your device unique stated address on the internet.
IP address are assigned by the internet assigned number authority. So, whatever the IP address you are getting, it is from the INM.
Inserting global uniqueness, where needed and managing a large address space for private network.
So, when you are in a corporate, when you are in office, you get a private IP address and when you are in internet, you get a public IP address.
So, each house have their private IP address. But when it connected to your router and router is communicating, router is taking your data packets to the internet. It goes through the ISP address.
I hope you understand what I am saying, that in your house or in your friend house, you both system have the same private IP address. But when your ISP, your router,
your host, tenant and your friend, router, host and tenant, they have different IP address. This IP address is decided by the internet service provider, whatever it is. Whatever the type of ISP provider you have in your location.
Now, type of IP address, we have IPv4, virtual phone person, IPv6. Now, majority of the company use IPv4 for their internal network.
The key function identification is there. This device on network has unique IP address for identification, location addressing.
It depends how data packets are formatted and send between devices, communication. IP work, hand in hand with TCP. TCP stands for transparency control protocol to establish virtual connection, forming the world in no TCP/IP suite.
We know TCP/IP.
This is the standard IPv4 address. IPv4 does a 32-bit integer. Simply expressed in dotted decimal notation.
In example, you can see it is the IPv4 address. They consist of four members, each are ranging from 0 to 25, separated by dots.
So, each segment represents an 8-bit pointy number in the update, which computer understand as 0 and 1. As a binary language.
Core function of IPv4, identification addressing, provider unique identifier for every device on the internet, allowing them to distinguish and look at it.
So, in a real world, there is a lot of diverse network and for efficiency, the data packaging encapsulate data into packet, adding a V IPv4 header with source and destination address for proper delivery.
Now, it is a logical addressing.
So, it should in a data packet, there will be IPv4, of source and receiver. That's why when it goes to internet.
Now, internet node, okay. So, this is the source and this is the destination. So, it will send to this logical address of IP.
This is how it works. It just like a mail.
We used post mail, we used, there was a post which we write down our letters on a paper and then send it to postman.
He will send according to receiver address and send it to the address. He will decide on which path, on which locations this letter will go to home. It's the same scenario is there.
From rotation, allow large data packet to be broken to smaller fragment, if an network maximum transfer is a unit is exceeded, then assemble at the destination.
At once IPv4 functions and limitations.
Service handling, QS strong for cold of service, and differentiated services, differ server to produce and group data packet based on application net, inserting critical data receiver, receive potential treatment.
Okay. Net network address translation, translate private app address within local network, single public address when communicating with internet, this effectively concept public app address.
This is what I'm talking about. Your friend and your house have same IP address inside, but when it goes out of router, they have different public address. It is called netting.
Your private IP address get changed to a public IP address.
Assuming drawback of IPv4, despite a robust functionality, IPv4 faces a significant challenge, it is a job exhaustion. With balance of people and multiple devices purpose coupled with their rapid growth of IPv4 and enterprise network, they will be only 4.3 billion in IPv4 address are simply not enough.
Well, technically like variable length subnet mass, realism and net, any team network address translation extra in its lab span the fundamental limitation led to development of IP version six offering a vast 34 zero unit clone.
It stresses like never and never and now class full addressing our so there will be a five type of classes in our IPv4 and each will be used for different purpose.
The most three are used basically and by remaining to over a reserve, we will talk of three year.
The first octet, okay, so first octet for the network prefix, while the remaining three octet for individual host number ideal for a very large network.
Class B uses the first two octet for does the network for the last two host numbers so they will form medium to large network uses the first octet for the network prefix and only the last octet for host number design for small network.
When you understand IP subnets, you have to go much more in deep, okay.
Finally, everything is in it. Okay, see this X below will can be a zero can be a one, okay, depending on the IP address you are having.
So host capacity where classes, the number of valuable host address within each class is determined by the number of bits allocated to host portion for example, the three bits are available to keep our three.
As fast weight, when we are saying it's to cube of two is eight possible home number can be assigned.
So class a host to 24 to keep to power 24 minus two unusual addresses.
Yes, same here to power 60 minus two unusual owners and two power eight minus two unusual addresses.
Why minus two for each network to decide reserve, okay, one for the network itself and one for the at desk broadcast address.
There are not assigned assignable to individual devices.
So in every 255 to our one for a broadcasting and one for a network itself always remember.
So dot one is for a gateway number, just like that. You have to remember when you work on that.
IP will force subnetting and CIDR.
So CIDR is 10 for class less entire domain routing and it will grow the rigid class for system become inefficient.
Last network world broken to smaller, whole version of subnet work.
Yeah, this little version of class less entire domain routing CIDR fundamentally change IP routing by removing the concept of IP.
At this class is instead a network profile.
Perfect is conveyed along with the mask indicating which could define the network and which define the host host.
So it will define that which part of our IP address is network and which part is the host.
There will be a no choice of octet only octet.
Okay, so here.
Subnetting device a large network in this modern logical segment.
So what is the subnet? It will divide.
There's a question always added by interview that what is the subnet?
The simplest of series dividing a bigger network into a small part.
The seven mark is determined the boundaries of the segment.
Consider the IP address.
Four, three, two, one, seven, two, two, five, two, five, five, dot, seven, one, slash, one, slash, one, slash, one, slash, one, slash, twenty seven, slash, twenty seven bits. Okay, of 32 bit address.
Other network bit and the Dominican five bits.
We have very many, there are five bits for host identification.
So we have total of 32 bits, twenty seven bits for network bits and remaining will be on our host identification.
Wow, now this is how it works.
We have to count from 0 0 1 0 1 0 1 1 like this.
And you have to count until 27 and it is a network remaining at the host.
Now IP address and network mask, our work.
IP address, we know logical addressing entries unique identifier for device one and work.
The third bit number used to differentiate the network portion from the host portion of IP address.
Yes, that what we did previously.
By only one, the seven marks one indicate it blow these bits belongs to a network.
And if you indicate it belongs to the host.
Okay.
So it's saying that if it is a one, it belongs to a network or zero, it belongs to a host in a segment mask.
Oh, it will see this in a more detail in next state in the next, we will do.
Classful versus classless addressing, classful addressing and the class with addressing is the most.
One, we can say one of the topic which interacts IP ranges.
We have fixed classes, ABC in a class full and class list.
There's a new fixed classes, subman wants to provide custom based on classes.
It can be a slash four slash eight, six slash 16 in class.
And it can be anything 20 to 30, 26, 24, 32, anything.
Sorry, 32 is not done.
But yeah, efficiency, waste IP, studio, rigid size.
And it's eight, they're 16.
So 24, so this is because there is a lot of IPs, which get waste, but because of the idea.
We can efficiently use a VIP example slash 24 and slash 26.
The second package of 20, 25, and special IPs, okay, so why use 25.
In boundary, 25, is triple one, eight times one.
This value is crucial in subman mask to designate that an interrupted belongs to an adverb portion.
Two five five dot two five five dot two five five dot zero means that first 24 bits and network bits, okay.
Network IP, this is the first type of address in the subnet where all whose bits are zero.
It identified the network itself and it's not assigned to a device, okay.
So it will identify it is assigned to a network itself, not true device.
And once six eight one dot six plus 24, the network IP is one and two one six eight one dot zero.
What is a broadcast IP?
So there will be an IP of last.
But because as you can see, this IP will be a result, all those bits are one.
It is used to send data to all devices and put the IP is one and two one six eight or one dot two five five.
So we just follow the understanding and then look at this approach first.
Let's move to IPv6.
It is protocol version six was introduced by the internet engineering task board and identify as a successor to IPv4 design to overcome the limitations of its predecessor.
IPv6 offers a significant advancement in terms of addressing address space efficiency and security.
So we don't take it present as a one twenty eight.
It's an excellent number to create this place in eight group separated by colon not dot here.
We use colon and there is a one twenty eight bit instead of third bit.
This was a space provider Stegrick trip for T and take a load.
So there is a like never ending addresses we have transitioned from IPv4 to v6.
For smooth migration, there will be dual Stegrick allowed us to run both IPv4 and v6 protocol.
Finally, encapsulate IPv6 packet within a v4 packet to translate. And there's a net, but translate between v4 to and v6 address in enable communication between host using different version.
It will enhance security.
Simplified header will be there and there's a quality of service will be higher quality order would end more optimizer.
And so IPv6 address unicast multicast and any cast.
So unicast addressing.
And if I was a single networking device packet sent to a unicast at deliver to the specific university, it formed the back of the most into the traffic and IPv6.
All it does except loop back multicast link local unicast and as un-specified address for another unicast connectivity.
In multicast address, you can also see the background, the image is there to understand what is actually unicast. It's one-to-one multicast to one-to-body.
So, address a group of interface typically across multiple groups of packet sent to multicast address is delivered to all interfaces within that different group.
So, v6 at multicast address are testing this path of fixed 0x capital Ff. This address type is a battle for application to carrying one-to-many communication such as vd conversing around and gaming.
Along for the facility, delivery of data to module will just be simultaneously. So, what is any cast addressing? Any cast addressing also identifies a group of interface, but a packet sent to any cast address is delivered only to the nearest interface.
Any cast is the one which will deliver to a nearest interface in that group.
The gentleman is a routing protocol. This is probably useful for service like DNS. In the last video, I told you to find out with a full form of DNS.
So, in, so this will be tax is still continued. If you know commando, where multiple servers can offer the same content and user are routed to the closet available server for improved performance and data density, data density, remember, but it will improve performance and redundancy.
So, as you know, the podcast addressing is the one in which it will broadcast, it has the efficiency of multicast and any cast addresses.
A poor guy does send data to all devices on a specific network or submit a click using the last IP and submit, which is at one dot 255. This might be compared to a local network and does not click cross, you know, to unless explicitly configure the removal would cost a V6 network overhead improve efficiency.
Now, what is the public private IP test. It is very important. It is very well good question that is explained to me.
So, let's start with the purpose. And used within a private network, land home network, used in a public internet. So, there is a private first and there is a public second.
Access will be not directly reset from antenna, because it is a private and dropped or routable and reasonable over the internet because of the public IP test. Let us change this.
Ten, one, one, two, one, six, one, nine, two, one, six, eight. All IP address, outside, reserved private engines translation required, netting, which is a network address translation, access internet does not record netting, cost free to use within the private network, because within a house,
it is workforce, but when you are going to communicate with the internet, you have to pay for that. So, there is an encoding cost. That's why ISP charge you some amount for providing the internet.
It will also include your ISP service as well as the IP address.
Understand this technique is also for an advertising security, stating that device can communicate both locally, globally. So, this is all about IPv4 and IPv6.
Just remember the classes of IPv4 have a, there is a difference between the v4 and v6. What is the public IP, what is the private IP, the difference between them.
And what, whatever the classes say, so just remember like the ranges of the classes of IPv4.
Like we have five classes in our network, in our ID.
Which range belongs to which, just example one to seven dot one dot zero dot zero dot one, which is a local, which is local host.
Two for testing purpose, it is always assigned to your system, but class A have some range. For example, one dot zero dot zero dot one two one two six dot two five five dot two five four.
So, it is for a class A. Similarly, for a class B, it's short form 128, no one zero dot zero dot zero dot zero dot zero dot zero dot two twenty three two five five two five five.
Class D 224 dot zero dot zero dot zero dot two two two thirty nine dot two five five two five five five, which is useful for broadcasting.
Class E for experimental purpose, these are the discipline, and it is to 40 dot two four zero dot zero dot zero dot zero dot two two five five two dot two five five dot two five five five two five. So, one interval tells us about the range is just 10 zero one twenty six for class A 128 to one at one class B 192 to two twenty three class C
two twenty four two thirty nine class D and two forty two two fifty five class E one twenty seven reserved for local host. You have to tell this.
Which class A for a beginner to a class B for mid range network and class C for smaller and T for digital form multicast and E for experimental purpose. That's all about the IPv4 VCS and to we can ask you and this is the information that enough for you to remember and thank you very much we will meet in our next video.
Bye-bye.